Thank you.
Gracias.
D-D-D-D-D-Dora
D-D-D-D-D-Dora  All right!
-D-D-D-D-D-Dora  -Let's go!
Dora, Dora, Dora the Explorer
Who's that super cool exploradora?
I'm a talking backpack!
And I'm a map with a mouth.
Grab your backpacks Let's go
Jump in, vamonos
You can lead the way
Swiper, no swiping!
Oh, man! Ooh!
Dora the Explorer!
Dora! Diego! It's time for dinner.
But, Mami, we're about to explore.
No. Now come on.
Besides, Diego has to be up early tomorrow.
He's moving to the city, remember?
His mom has a new job.
Oh, yeah. I remember.
Dora, what did we say about dressing up Boots?
He's a wild monkey, honey. He's not meant to be in human clothes.
-This is delicious! -Wow, this is good.
-Mmm! -¡Delicioso!
Can you say "delicioso"?
Say "delicioso"!
She'll grow out of it.
Mmm.
¡Delicioso!
Don't start. Just gotta let it go.
Tio, what is Parapata?
Parapata is a great Inca legend.
.
An ancient city...
now lost in time.
Explorers for hundreds of years
have been searching for it in vain.
And, well, ever since we moved here to the jungle,
we've been trying to find it.
Is there gold there?
Stories say there's more gold there
than the rest of the world combined.
So when we find it, do we get to keep the gold?
-Um... -No, no. Nobody keeps the gold.
We want to document Parapata for archeological purposes.
See, we're explorers, we're not treasure hunters.
And as explorers, well, then the discovery of new places...
that's the treasure.
-What? -I don't get it.
Okay, Cole, honey, they're six.
Treasure hunting bad, exploring good.
-Oh. -Okay.
I just said that!
Eh. Not really.
I bet the lost city of Parapata
有叢林貓的金色雕像
has golden statues of jungle cats.
和猴子 像靴子一樣
And monkeys. Like Boots.
猴子是最好的
Monkeys are the best.
不可能！捷豹更酷
No way! Jaguars are way cooler.
猴子可以擺動和攀爬 和我們交談
Monkeys can swing and climb and talk to us.
不 他們不能
No, they can't.
靴子不跟你說話
Boots isn't talking to you.
他會說話
He can talk.
我更清楚！我比你大
I know better! I'm older than you.
我想 你對我大喊大叫
I think you're just yelling at me
因為你很傷心 你要離開
because you're sad you're leaving.
當然 這就是我對你大喊大叫的原因
Of course that's why I'm yelling at you.
我會想你的 迭戈
我也會想你的 妹妹
還有靴子(小猴)
留給永遠最好的朋友
Keep this. Best friends forever.
直到我們的下一次冒險 第一
Until our next adventure, prima.
Till our next adventure, primo.
-來吧 迭戈 -瓦莫斯
-Come on, Diego. -Vamos.
再見 朵拉
Adios, Dora.
迭戈！
Diego!
10年後
我是朵拉 我被一群憤怒的侏儒大象追趕
Hi! I'm Dora! And I'm being chased by a herd of angry pygmy elephants.
你能說"憤怒的侏儒象"嗎？
Can you say, "angry pygmy elephants"?
祝你下次好運 憤怒的大象
Better luck next time, angry elephants.
原諒我 黑凱曼...
Pardon me, black caiman...
亞馬遜最大的捕食者
largest predator in the Amazon.
哦 寶貝們
Aw, babies.
再見！
Bye!
這是靴子！
And that's Boots!
嗨 靴子
Hi, Boots.
嗨 朵拉 今天的冒險是什麼？
"Hi, Dora. What's today's adventure?"
今天 我們繼續長達數十年的帕拉帕塔搜尋
Today, we continue our decades-long search for Parapata.
哦 看！
Ooh, look!
金毒青蛙
Golden poison frog.
它的皮膚有致命的毒性 並可能導致全身麻痹
Its skin is lethally toxic and can cause full-body paralysis.
你能說"嚴重的神經毒性"嗎？
Can you say, "severe neurotoxicity"?
再見 致命的青蛙 祝你好運
Bye, deadly frog. Have a nice day.
哦！落石！
Oh! A rockfall!
這個山洞以前不在這裏
This cave wasn't here before.
對不起 毛茸茸的吸血鬼蝙蝠家族
Sorry, hairy-legged vampire bat family.
哦
Ohh.
古印卡
Ancient Inca.
帕拉帕塔
Parapata.
來吧 靴子
Come on, Boots.
如果你相信自己 任何事情都是可能的
If you just believe in yourself, anything is possible.
我沒事 靴子！
I'm okay, Boots!
呃...你能去幫我找媽媽和爸爸嗎？
Uh... Could you maybe go and get Mami and Papi for me?
嘿 我能看看雕像了嗎？
Hey, now can I see the statue?
-你砍完木頭了嗎？-是的
-Did you finish chopping the wood? -Yeah.
親愛的 你今天嚇死我們了 如果靴子沒有找到我們...
Honey, you scared us to death today. If Boots hadn't found us...
對不起 只是我確信這是帕查庫蒂統治時期
I'm sorry. It's just I'm pretty sure it's from the reign of Pachacuti.
我是說 這些標記 它們看起來像某種...
I mean, the markings, they look like some sort of...
-地圖 -什麼？
-Map. -What?
地圖！
A map!
就是這樣
This is it.
這是丟失的部分
This is the missing piece.
我們找到帕拉帕塔了！
We found Parapata!
等等 你們為什麼不...興奮？
Wait, why aren't you guys... more excited?
呃...
Uh...
-你們想通了 不是嗎？-什麼？
-You guys figured it out, didn't you? -What?
-你知道帕拉帕塔在哪裏 -不
-You know where Parapata is. -No.
你用紅線標出來了
You red-tacked it.
-我們做到了？-我們沒有標出
-We did? -We never use the red tack.
-你知道它在哪裏 -我們應該等紅色的大頭針
-You know where it is! -We should have waited on the red tack.
-毫無疑問 這是個糟糕的決定 -好吧 我們確實搞清楚了
-Definitely, definitely bad call. -Okay, we did figure it out.
-印加到秘魯的一個地區
--The Inca reached an area in Peru
沒人相信會是這裏
that nobody thought was possible.
那是你和媽媽要找到帕拉帕塔的地方
And that's where your mother and I are gonna find Parapata.
還有我
And me.
對不起 寶貝 你還沒準備好 今天就證明了這一點
I'm sorry, sweetie, you're just not ready, and you proved that to us today.
不 不 不 我準備好了 媽媽...
No, no, no, I'm ready, Mami...
對不起 我們已經下定決心了
I'm sorry, but we've made up our minds.
-媽媽... -不
-Mami... -No.
親愛的
Honey...
你知道叢林
you do know the jungle.
這是你的一部分
It's a part of you.
但是你獨自一人
But you're all alone out there.
為什麼這是件壞事？
And why is that a bad thing?
因為我們不會總是在那裏把你拉上來
Because we won't always be there to pull you up.
去城裏吧 交個朋友
Go to the city. Make friends.
朵拉 快點！你有航班要趕
Dora, hurry! You have a flight to catch.
但是我不想去城裏
But I don't want to go to the city.
-我不認識那裏的人 -你會認識你的家人的
-I won't know anyone there. -You'll know your family.
是的 你以前離迭戈很近 我敢打賭他也很想念你
Yeah, you used to be so close to Diego. I'll bet he's missed you, too.
-關鍵是 我想你這個年紀...
--The point is, I think it would be good...
和朋友在一起會更好
for you to be in the world around kids your own age.
-可能有用 -有什麼用？
-It might help. -Help what?
親愛的 你脖子上戴了條圍巾
Honey, you're wearing a boa around your neck.
我知道
I know.
-是圍巾...是像圍巾 -真有趣
-It's a boa... as a boa. -That's funny.
-把圍巾放下-親愛的 還有些事我們要討論
-Put the boa down. -Honey, there's something else we gotta discuss.
-我能處理-好吧
-I can handle this. -Okay.
坐下 小姐
Take a seat, young lady.
-發生什麼事了？-來吧
-What's happening? -Come on.
我們要談談
We're gonna have a talk.
關於大城市的危險
About the dangers of the big city.
你會被邀請參加一些聚會
See, you're gonna be invited to some parties.
其中一些派對 他們被稱為"狂歡"
And some of these parties, they're called "raves."
那裏的人被稱為狂歡者
The people there are called ravers.
是的 他們喜歡發光棒
Yeah, and they love glow sticks
還有項鏈和麻袋
and candy necklaces and Hacky Sacks.
音樂 聽起來像這樣
The music, it sounds like this:
無法阻止它
Can't stop it
跟上
Go get it
是的 它很有活力 很有活力
Yeah, it's very aggressive. Very aggressive.
是的
Yeah.
好
Okay.
嗯 小心點 這就是我們要說的
Well, be careful. That's what we want to say.
-我應該說的 -我想會更容易些
-I should've just said that. -I think it would've been easier.
親愛的 這是你的衛星電話 隨時給我們打電話
Honey, here's your satellite phone. Call us anytime.
您可以在地圖上跟蹤我們的坐標
And you can track our coordinates on your map.
但是 情況不一樣
But it's not the same.
我是探險家 像你一樣
I'm an explorer, like you.
哦 親愛的 你有整個世界去探索！
Oh, honey, you have the whole world to explore!
去看看吧
Go see it.
交朋友
Make friends.
這是真正的探索
That's real exploring.
但
But...
我不知道怎麼做
I don't know how.
是的 你會的
Yes, you do.
做你自己 朵拉 好嗎？
Just be yourself, Dora. Okay?
加油 你快錯過你的航班了
Come on. You're gonna miss your flight.
我愛你
Te quiero.
朵拉
Dora...
城裏沒有猴子
no monkeys in the city.
她知道 夥計
She knows, buddy.
哇！
Wow!
你好！我是朵拉！"索伊朵拉！
Hi! I'm Dora! ¡Soy Dora!
我是朵拉！你好！
I'm Dora! Hi!
很高興見到你 你好！
It's nice to meet you. Hi!
-你看到她了嗎？-沒有
-Do you see her? -No.
如果我們認不出她怎麼辦？
What if we don't recognize her?
對不起！對不起！
Excuse me! Sorry!
-對不起！對不起！-嘿 看！
-Excuse me! Sorry! -Hey, watch it!
-我覺得不會的 -對不起！對不起！
-I don't think that's gonna be a problem. -Excuse me! Sorry!
朵拉！歡迎來到這個城市
Dora! Welcome to the city.
薩布麗娜姨媽！
Tia Sabrina!
-還有西奧·尼科！-朵拉！
-And Tio Nico! -Dora!
你好！我非常想念你們
Hi! I missed you guys so much.
-迭戈！-嗯 嗨
-And Diego! -Uh, hi.
哇！
Wow!
哇！你這麼瘦又高！像一棵棕櫚樹
Wow! You're so skinny and tall! Like a palmito tree.
你都不像你了
You don't even look like you.
-嗯...謝謝？-我們會玩得很開心的！
-Um... thank you? -We're gonna have so much fun!
你比我記得的更有活力
You are way more energetic than I remember.
我們走吧！
Let's go!
-啊 朵拉 -奶奶！
-Ah, Dora. -¡Abuelita!
哦 我想念你！
Oh, I missed you!
看看你！都成大姑娘了！
Look at you! Such a big girl!
還是這麼活潑
And still with the bangs.
哇！
Wow!
粉紅色
It's so pink.
我很喜歡
And everything matches.
是的 我父母知道你會喜歡的
Yeah, my parents thought you'd like it.
嘿 我給你帶了些東西
Hey, I brought you something.
什麼？
What is that?
在你離開叢林之前 我們分開的糖果 記得嗎？
The candy bar that we split before you left the jungle. Remember?
你的呢？
Where's yours?
嗯...
Um...
我 可能吃了它
Well, I... probably ate it.
就像十年前一樣
Like ten years ago.
哦
Oh.
對不起 我...
Sorry. I'm...
我只是覺得我們要
I just thought that we were gonna
再次將他們重新混在一起
mush them back together again.
太酷了
It's cool.
這將是偉大的！
This is gonna be great!
好 嗯...
Okay. Well...
你應該睡一覺
you should get some sleep.
晚安 第一
Good night, prima.
晚安 表弟
Buenas noches, primo.
好
Okay.
嗯嗯？嗯
Mm? Mmm.
-離車遠點！把手放在我們能看見的地方！
--Step away from the vehicle! Hands where we can see 'em!
背包 背包
Backpack, backpack
背包裏裝滿了東西
On the backpack loaded up with things
還有小玩意兒 太多了
And knickknacks, too
你在唱什麼？
Um, what are you singing?
我總是唱歌 幫我記住要帶什麼
I always sing. Helps me remember what to bring.
哇！
Wow!
什麼？
What?
我們就是這樣去學校的？
This is how we get to school?
等等 你介意嗎？
Hold on. Do you mind?
脫下它
Just take that off.
整理一下
Do a little of that.
-嗯 -這是適合當地人的嗎？
-Hm. -Is this to fit in with the indigenous people?
-我只是想讓你第一天過得愉快 -嗯
-I just want you to have a good first day. -Mm.
如果我不跟你說話 也不要和別人說 好嗎？
And if I don't talk to you, don't take it personal, okay?
我們都只是想在高中生存下來
We're all just trying to survive high school.
這是一個可怕的噩夢
It's a horrible nightmare.
做你自己
Just be yourself.
我是新來的！你叫什麼名字？
I'm new here! What's your name?
哇
Wow.
哇！
Whoa!
好的 孩子 袋子 桌子
Okay, young lady. Bag, table.
你好 朵拉 這是背包
Hola, soy Dora. And this is Backpack.
是的
Yeah.
-這是什麼？-緊急情況下用的
-What is this? -A flare. In case of emergency.
哦
Oh.
它著了！
It works!
哦 這些是什麼？
Oh, and what are these?
碘丸消毒水
Iodine pills to sanitize water.
個人發電機
Personal generator.
雙向無線電
Two-way radio.
五天緊急食品供應包
Five-day emergency food supply kit.
一個帳篷 還有雙層吊床
OneLink Shelter System with DoubleNest Hammock.
你知道 懸崖睡覺
You know, for cliff sleeping.
你不能把這些帶進來
You can't bring any of this in here.
放學後把它撿起來
Pick it up after school.
這是怎麼回事？
What's going on?
但我可以帶我的溜溜球來嗎？
But I can bring my yo-yo?
你意識到溜溜球是我最致命的武器
You realize that a yo-yo is by far my deadliest weapon.
真的？
Really?
對不起 我們遲到了 朵拉 我們走
I'm sorry. We're late. Dora, let's go.
來吧 我們走！
Come on, let's go!
慈善蛋糕！
Cupcakes for charity!
拯救雨林！慈善蛋糕！
Save the rain forest! Cupcakes for charity!
-雨林怎麼了？-它被摧毀了
-What happened to the rain forest? -It's being destroyed.
哦不！哪一個？
Oh, no! Which one?
丹特裏？亞西尼？埃爾·雲克？湯加斯？卡庫姆？
Daintree? Yasuni? El Yunque? Hoh? Tongass? Kakum?
呃...全部？
Uh... all of them?
亞馬遜雨林正面臨著
Ranching and agriculture are some of the greatest threats
牧場和農業最大的威脅
facing the Amazon today.
但我相信 重點保護
But I believe that with focused conservation
和植物性飲食
and plant-based diets,
我們可以幫助雨林再次茁壯成長
we can help the rain forest thrive again.
你是誰？
Who are you?
你很聰明嗎？
Why are you smart?
你在我的學校做什麼？
And what are you doing in my school?
朵拉 在家接受教授教育
Dora. Home-schooled by professors.
父母錯誤地認為我不負責任 缺乏社會經驗
Parents misjudged me as irresponsible and lacking in socialization.
哦
Oh.
吃一個房子蛋糕
Have a cupcake on the house.
謝謝！
Thank you!
-今天過得愉快-你也是 再見！
-Have a great day. -You, too. Bye!
-她看起來不錯 -不
-She seems nice. -She's not.
那是薩米·摩爾
That's Sammy Moore.
她是個榮譽學生
She's an honor roll student,
三校運動員和班長
tri-varsity athlete and class president.
哦 所以她一定很佩服她的同齡人
Oh, so she must be very admired by her peers.
什麼 她？不可能
What, her? No way.
每個人都討厭她 她簡直就是地球上最差的人
Everyone hates her. She's literally, like, the worst person on Earth.
你好！我是朵拉！很酷的襯衫
Hi! I'm Dora! Cool shirt.
哇！
Whoa!
我們不在那裏
We're not there.
地球 我們更像是...這裏
Earth. We're more like over... here.
要我糾正它嗎？
Want me to correct it?
啊
Ah.
我們開始吧
There we go.
你 懂天文學？
You... into astronomy?
當然 有誰不懂？
Of course I am. Who isn't?
-那是什麼？有問題嗎？
--What's that? Is there a problem?
那是早鍾 我們現在遲到了 謝謝
That's the morning bell. We're late now. Thank you.
哦 再見 這是一個紙杯蛋糕
Oh, goodbye. Here's a cupcake.
-謝謝！-那是蘭迪·沃倫
-Thank you! -That's Randy Warren.
你也不要和他說話 好嗎？
You don't want to talk to him, either, okay?
為什麼？
Why?
所以
That's why.
好吧 讓我們看看昨晚誰讀了
Okay, let's see who did the reading last night.
誰是莫比·迪克...
Who is Moby Dick...
為什麼這個故事今天仍然很重要？
and why is this story still significant today?
哦
Oh.
謝天謝地 還有一個
Thank God. Someone else.
你是新來的 是嗎？
You're new, yes?
好吧 打個招呼
Well, say hello.
你好 我是朵拉 迭戈的表親
Hola. I'm Dora. I'm Diego's cousin.
莫比·迪克是一頭鯨魚
And Moby Dick is a whale.
這部小說是西方作家的典範
The novel exemplifies the Western writer's
對殖民化土著文化的懷舊佔有
nostalgic appropriation of colonized indigenous cultures,
解釋了它在今天的美國小說中被重新化的地位
which explains its reified status in American fiction today.
你從哪兒轉來 朵拉？
Where did you transfer from, Dora?
叢林
The jungle.
我的父母都是教授 我讀了很多書
My parents are both professors. I do a lot of reading.
呆子！
Dork-a!
謝謝你 朵拉
Thank you, Dora.
看起來我們班上有一顆新星
It looks like we have a new star in the class.
不確定 我早些時候說得很清楚
Not sure I made myself clear earlier.
但是 如果你要向女王開槍 你最好不要錯過
But if you're going to take a shot at the queen, you better not miss.
沒有什麼比受傷的動物更危險了
There is nothing more dangerous than a wounded animal.
很多事情比受傷的動物更危險
A lot of things are more dangerous than a wounded animal.
-好好開始吧 -停下！停下
-A healthy one, for a start. -Stop! Just... stop.
我在盯著你
I'm watching you.
再見 大家！今天工作很出色！
Goodbye, everyone! Great job today!
我們成功了！我們學完了！
We did it! We finished school!
如果你該去一個地方
If there's a place You gotta go
你要知道 我是地圖
I'm the one you need to know I'm the map
我的孩子在學校怎麼樣?都還好嗎
很好！
Great!
是的 很好 完美
Yeah. Great. Perfect.
-好吧 -嗨 親愛的 你好嗎？
-Okay. -Hi, honey, how are you?
-我們做得很好 但仔細聽
--We're doing great. But listen carefully.
-好吧 -我們在坐標1.832處
-Okay. -We're at coordinates 1.832.
我們正在取得非常好的進展
We're making really good progress.
呃...對不起？嗯...
Uh... Excuse me? Um...
我有點卡住了！
I'm kind of stuck!
我不知道你是否能聽到我 但坐標是2.3674
I don't know if you can hear me, but the coordinates are 2.3674.
我想你！
I miss you!
嗯 你試過這個嗎？太不可思議了！
Mmm. Have you tried this? It's incredible!
-它叫什麼？-奶酪
-What's it called? -Mac 'n' cheese.
謝謝！幹得好！
Thank you! Great job!
美味！
¡Delicioso!
請輸入您的語音
Please record your message.
媽媽 爸爸 又是我
Mami, Papi, it's me again.
你在哪裏？請給我打電話
Where are you? Please call me.
請語音留言
Please leave a message at the tone.
-嗨 媽媽 爸爸 方便的時候 給我打電話
--Hola, mami, papi. Call me when you can.
我們星期五要去自然歷史博物館
We're going to the Natural History Museum Friday.
想你 想靴子 懷念所有
Miss you, miss Boots. Miss everything.
沒有你 沒有你
Without you Without you
冬之舞
12月12日
成為你最喜歡的明星
你是太陽 我明白了
You're the sun. I get it.
你是氫！
And you're hydrogen!
-哦 -這就是星星的構成
-Oh. -That's what stars are made of.
我喜歡這首歌！
I love this song!
你想跳舞嗎？
You want to dance?
對不起 朵拉 我真的不會跳舞
Sorry, Dora, I can't really dance.
-好吧 -但是...
-Okay. -But...
不過 我可以屏住呼吸7分鐘
I can hold my breath for seven minutes, though.
我父母讓我在社區游泳池裏無人監督
My parents left me unsupervised at the community pool a lot.
假裝淹死是引起注意的好方法
Pretending to drown is a good way to get attention.
想要 想看嗎？
Wanna... Wanna see?
我喜歡跳舞
I love dancing.
我真的很喜歡
I'm really good at it.
-孔雀！-現在大家圍攏過來
-The Peacock! -Everybody gather round now
轉過身 轉過身去
Turn around, turn around.
哦 哦 哦 哦 哦 哦
Oh, oh. Oh, oh, oh.
這是節奏
It's the rhythm
在島上
Of the island
像甘蔗 那麼甜
And like sugar cane So sweet
嘿 看！是笨蛋舞蹈！
Hey, look! It's Disco Dork-a!
大象！
The Elephant!
哦！哦！
Ooh! Ooh!
-看 看 -哦 天哪 她要轉學了
-Look, look, look. -Oh, my gosh. She's going to have to transfer schools.
來吧 第一
Come on, primo.
你知道這個舞蹈！
You know this one. Dance!
-大猩猩！-跳舞 迭戈 跳舞！
-The Gorilla! -Dance, Diego, dance!
跳舞 迭戈 跳舞！跳舞 迭戈 跳舞！
Dance, Diego, dance! Dance, Diego, dance!
跳舞 迭戈 跳舞！
Dance, Diego, dance!
迭戈 等等！
Diego, wait!
至少我讓人們跳舞和鼓掌
At least I got people dancing and clapping.
他們在嘲笑你
They were mocking you.
他們在嘲笑你和我！
They were laughing at you and me!
你在這裏幾個星期了 你怎麼看不到？
You've been here for weeks. How do you not see that?
我看到了 我不笨
I see it. I'm not stupid.
但我必須做我自己 這就是我所知道的
But I have to be myself. That's all I know how to do.
好吧 別再干了
Well, just stop doing it.
就像有一天 停止做自己
For, like, one day just stop being you
這才正常
and just be normal.
迭戈 我們過去很親近 現在為什麼這樣？
Diego, we used to be so close. Why are things so different now?
朵拉 因為這不是叢林
Because, Dora, this isn't the jungle,
在那裏你可以做任何你想做的事
where you can just do whatever you want
和猴子成為最好的朋友
and be best friends with a monkey.
這是高中 是生死
This is high school. It's life or death.
已經足夠難了 不必照顧班上的怪人
And it was hard enough already without having to take care of the class weirdo.
朵拉？
Dora?
好吧
Okay.
有時候我們都需要躲藏 不是嗎？
Sometimes we all need to hide. No?
我想 我從未感到孤獨
I guess... I never felt lonely
當我一個人在叢林裏的時候
when I was by myself in the jungle.
但現在我和他們在一起
But now that I'm surrounded by kids,
我一直感到孤獨
I feel alone all the time.
-我想迭戈討厭我 -啊
-I think Diego hates me. -Ah.
不
No.
你是我們的家人？
You are familia, mi amor. Huh?
-奶奶 -嗯？
-Abuelita. -Hm?
我是怪人嗎？
Am I a weirdo?
嗯嗯
Mm...
沒有比我們輕鬆的人
no more than the rest of us.
也不是沒有
That's not a "no."
給你拿些炸薯條 好嗎？
Let's get you some frijolitos, okay?
好的 這是尋寶者名單
Okay, here's the scavenger hunt list.
你們知道怎麼做
You know the drill.
四人組組 去拍一些照片
Team up in groups of four and go get some photos.
哦 如果有人需要我 我會在自助餐廳...
Oh, and if anybody needs me, I'll be in the cafeteria...
質疑我的生活選擇
questioning my life choices.
-我能參加你的隊伍嗎？-你們需要第四個人嗎？
-Can I be on your team? -Do you guys need a fourth person?
嘿 夥計們 我們四個人？
Hey, guys, us four?
我能參加你的團隊嗎？
Can I be on your team?
-嘿 夥計們 -我能參加你的隊伍嗎？
-Hey, guys. -Can I be on your team?
你開玩笑吧
You've got to be kidding me.
嗯.
Hm.
當然 這種情況正在發生
Of course this is happening.
你們兩個之間有些不愉快
There's something really icy happening between you two.
-是笨蛋舞蹈嗎？-我很高興你提出來...
-Was it the Disco Dork-a dance? -Well, I'm glad you brought it up...
我只是開玩笑 其實我不在乎
I'm just kidding, I don't actually care.
好 找到一些超過1000年的歷史
Okay. "Find something that's more than 1,000 years old.
最古老的遺物 給加兩分 加油！
Oldest relic gets two extra points." Come on!
哦 天哪 你能更專橫嗎？
Oh, my gosh. Could you be any bossier?
-不好意思 我是"施令者"-是的
-Excuse me? "Bossier." Really? -Yeah.
下一步如何？不依不饒？還是我太為難你？
What's next? "Shrill?" Or am I being too "difficult" for you?
你要從厭女101中走出來
You left that out of your Misogyny 101 class.
什麼？你有什麼要說的嗎？
What? Do you have something to say?
我現在太害怕了
I'm just so scared right now.
這是埃及展覽呢？
What about this Egyptian exhibit?
任何埃及人都是迄今為止最古老的遺跡
Anything Egyptian would be the oldest relic by far.
-夥計們？-噓
-Guys? -Psst.
我想 我也許能幫助你
I think I may be able to help you.
無意中聽說了你的尋寶
Overheard about your scavenger hunt.
你在看埃及的海報
You were looking at the Egyptian posters.
-什麼時候打開？-哦 這就是問題所在 兩個星期
-When does it open? -Oh, that's the problem, two weeks.
他們今天在地下室卸貨
They're unloading it today in the basement.
看 如果這對你意義重大
Look... If it means that much to you,
可能有辦法讓你下去
there may be a way for you to get down there.
最好不要是 追逐野鵝(白費力氣)
This best not be some wild goose chase.
我當然希望是 我喜歡追逐野鵝
I sure hope it is. I love chasing wild geese.
直到你抓到一個 那就不好玩了
Until you catch one. Then it is not fun.
被捉的鵝是最發狂的！
A caught goose is just the meanest!
按起源分組 古埃及的東西 應該在這個通道
Well, it's grouped by origin, so the Ancient Egyptian stuff should be in this aisle.
-誰 -哦
-Whoa. -Oh.
-嗨 -哦 不 她被抓了！
-Hi. -Oh, no, she's been caught!
我可以解釋 我為什麼在這裏
And I can totally explain why I'm here.
-有人來了 -跟我來 小姐
-Someone's coming. -Come with me, miss.
隱藏！隱藏！
Hide! Hide!
-哪裏？-那裏 那裏！
-Where? -There, there, there!
看看我發現了什麼偷偷摸摸的
Look what I found sneaking around.
啊 穿插器
Ah. An interloper.
小偷
A thief.
或者是探險家
Or maybe an explorer.
-嗨 朵拉-嗨 我是朵拉
-Hola, Dora. -Hi, I'm Dora, and...
等等 你已經知道我的名字了？
Wait, you already knew my name?
嘿 你得幫我
Hey. You gotta help me.
我想我們贏了尋寶
I guess we win the scavenger hunt.
什麼？嘿 不
What? Hey, no.
放開我！
Let me go!
-嘿 不！-等等 等等
-Hey, no! -Wait, wait, wait.
-怎麼了？-這是尋寶遊戲嗎？
-What's going on? -Is this a scavenger hunt?
你們在這裏幹什麼？
What are you guys doing in here?
好好睡 朵拉 當你醒來時
Sleep tight, Dora, and when you wake up,
你會幫我們 找到你的父母 然後...帕拉帕塔
you will help us find your parents, and then... Parapata.
發生了什麼事情？
What's happening?
我們在哪？
Where are we?
我認為 我們將從飛機上運走
I think... we're being unloaded from a plane.
我們不是在飛機上 我們不能
We're not on a plane. We can't...
哦 天哪 我們在飛機上！哦
Oh, my God, we're on a plane! Oh...
我們沒有身份證就離開了這個國家
We've left the country without ID.
我們需要提醒美國領事館
We need to alert the US consulate.
朵拉 發生什麼事了？
Dora, what happened?
他們要綁架我 找我爸媽  找到帕拉帕塔
你是認真的嗎？
他們是尋寶者？
They're treasure hunters?
我為什麼要說普通話？
Why did I take Mandarin?
你們在說什麼？
What are you guys saying?
我們得離開這裏
We gotta get out of here.
哦 大家看 朵拉帶了把刀去實地考察
Oh, look, Dora brought a knife on the field trip, everybody.
我看到三個僱傭兵武裝
I see three mercenaries. Armed.
等等 還有第四個
Wait, there's a fourth.
我想他看見我了
I think he saw me.
-他來找我們了 -啊！
-He's coming for us. -Ah!
-好吧 我不在這裏 -我是化身
-Okay. I am not here. -I'm an avatar.
朵拉！是你！
Dora! It is you!
-你是誰？-我是你父母的朋友
-Who are you? -I'm a friend of your parents.
我在救你 朵拉！
I'm rescuing you, Dora!
如果你想活下去 跟我來...
Come with me if you want to live...
他去哪兒了？
Where did he go?
...他死了嗎？
Did... Did he die?
我沒事！我沒事 我需要你的幫助
I'm okay! I'm okay. I need your help.
但是我們必須逃跑 現在！
But we have to run. Now!
老闆！
Boss!
抓住他們！
Get them!
我父母沒有在叢林許可單上簽字！
My parents did not sign a permission slip for the jungle!
我們為什麼在這裏？
Why are we here?
博物館在哪裏？為什麼 為什麼？
Where's the museum? Why, why, why?
-我們怎麼離開這裏？-我不知道！
-How do we get out of here? -I don't know!
-就我的計劃而言 把你從箱子裏弄出來
-Getting you out of the box was as far as my plan went. -Huh?
呵呵！猛擊者準備！
Huh! Swiper at the ready!
不管發生什麼事 拿地圖
Whatever happens, get that map.
猛擊者 收到
Swiper, yes, swiping.
這是什麼救援？
What kind of rescue is this?
這是你唯一能做的
It's the only one you've got.
這裏 讓我試試
Here. Let me try.
-嗨 -什麼...
-Hola. -What the...
嘿！那只狐貍剛剛偷了我的地圖！
Hey! That fox just swiped my map!
在哪兒？在哪兒？
Where is it? Where is it? Where is it?
狐貍偷了我的地圖 來吧 幫幫我！
What part of, "The fox just swiped my map" don't you understand? Come on, help me!
來拿啊！給你 我的小朋友
Gotcha! There you are, my little friend.
別跑 你...你 猛擊者！
No swiping, you... you... swiper!
是啊 哦！哦！
Yeah, oh! Oh!
哦！
Ohh!
她太神奇了
She's amazing.
哦 哦 哦哦哦！
Whoa, whoa, whoa. Uh-oh!
哦 中槍！
Oh, shoot!
人 我被顛倒了
Man! I'm stuck upside-down.
猛擊者 不...
Swiper, no...
-幹得好 猛擊者 -我知道 夥計
-Good job, Swiper. -I know, man.
抓住她！
Get her!
朵拉！
Dora!
-現在我們怎麼辦？-來吧 來吧！
-Now what do we do? -Come on, come on!
-我們的救援人員去哪了？-他逃跑了！
-Where did our rescuer go? -He ran away!
-進來！-打開這扇門 夥計！
-Get in! -Open this door, man!
-進來！-我不是在開玩笑！
-Get in! -I'm not joking, man!
毒蛇 上車！別讓他們逃跑！
Viper, get the truck! Don't let them escape!
-等一下！-哦！
-Hold on! -Ohh!
對不起！
Sorry!
他們在追嗎？
Are they following?
他們去哪兒了？
Where have they gone?
這是唯一的路 仔細找
This is the only road for miles. Keep your eyes peeled.
沒事了
Not anymore.
你們還好嗎？孩子
Are you kids okay?
哦
Oh.
-不好 -不好？
-Not really. -"Not really"?
對本世紀的輕描淡寫
Understatement of the century.
我剛被壞人綁架和追趕！
I was just kidnapped and chased by bad guys!
一隻戴著面具的狐貍！大家都看到了 對吧？
And a fox with a mask! Everyone saw that, right?
為什麼那只狐貍戴面具？
Like, why does that fox need to remain anonymous?
誰會認出一隻狐貍？
Who is gonna recognize one specific fox?
-嗯 -你怎麼知道我的名字？
-Mm. -How did you know my name?
我最後一次見到你 你還是個嬰兒
You were an infant the last time I saw you.
我叫亞歷杭德羅·古鐵雷斯 古代語言的教授
My name is Alejandro Gutierrez. I'm a professor of ancient languages
在秘魯利馬的聖馬科斯大學
at San Marcos University in Lima, Peru.
你父母和我經常聯繫
Your parents and I were in constant contact during their time here.
兩周前 你父母的電話沒有了
Then two weeks ago, your parents' calls stopped.
從那以後...再沒聯繫
Since then... silencio.
-那意味著沉默 -是的 我很沉默
-That means silence. -Yeah. I got that one.
他們幾周沒接我打來的電話了
They haven't answered any of my sat phone call for weeks, either.
你父親一周前就寄給我 讓我幫忙
Your father sent me this just a week before, in case I could help.
啊 爸爸的日記！
Ah, Papi's journal!
所以我來這裏是為了確保他們沒事
So I came here to make sure they were okay.
跟蹤他們到目前為止
Tracked them this far.
我一直在想 希望得到他們的一個信號
I've been staking it out, hoping for a sign from them.
我看見你從箱子裏探出頭 我對自己說 朵拉！
And then I saw you poke your head out of that crate and I said to myself, "Dora!"
朵拉...被綁架的少年！
Dora the... kidnapped teenager!
但是你是怎麼認出我的？
But how did you recognize me?
你看起來完全一樣
Well, you look sort of exactly the same.
但 我不知道在哪找到你的父母
But... I'm afraid I have no idea where to find your parents.
不用擔心 我可以在叢林裏追蹤我的父母
Don't worry. I can track my parents in the jungle.
我們走吧！
Let's go!
等等
Hold up.
或者我們可以叫當地警察
Or we could call the local police
讓他們來救我們 就像特警隊一樣
and have them come rescue us with, like, a SWAT team.
嗯 是的 這聽起來像是對的選擇
Hmm. Yeah, that sounds like another solid option.
答案是肯定的！
Of course!
你好？911 你能來找我們嗎？
Hello? 911? Can you please come and get us?
我們在雨林的拐角處
We're at the corner of Rain and Forest.
好了 我知道了！我只想回家
Okay, I get it! I just want to go home.
我們會死在這裏
We're gonna die out here.
看看你周圍
Look around you.
這是人們死亡的地方
This is the kind of place where people die.
從某種意義上說 每個地方都是人們死亡的地方
I mean, in a way, every place is the kind of place where people die.
-好吧 那是個愚蠢的概念-夥計們
-Okay, well, that's a bummer notion. -Guys, guys.
聽著 找到朵拉的父母是我們回家的最好機會
Listen, finding Dora's parents is our best chance of getting home.
我姑姑和叔叔會知道該怎麼做
My aunt and uncle will know what to do.
朵拉是我的表妹 我不能讓她去...
Dora's my cousin, I can't just let her go off with some...
我們剛剛遇到壞人
strange and anxious man we just met.
謝謝你 迭戈
Thank you, Diego.
現在讓我們去找朵拉的父母
Now let's go find Dora's parents.
看！在那裏！那是他們的車！
Look! In there! That's their car!
這裏 就是這樣 我們的家庭象徵
Here. This is it. Our family symbol.
-這是他們徒步旅行的地方 -我們去那嗎？
-This is where they started hiking. -Are we there?
你父母呢？我沒看見你父母
Where are your parents? I don't see your parents.
我們不能再開車了
We can't go any further by car.
-叢林太密了-那我們怎麼...
-The jungle gets too dense. -So how do we...
我們必須步行進入叢林
We must enter the jungle on foot.
幸運的是 我為這種可能性做好了準備
Luckily, I prepared for this possibility.
好吧 我可能有點過度了
Okay, I may have gone a little overboard on supplies.
請便
Be my guest.
這是一場合理的噩夢！
This is a legit nightmare!
不過 我不會先去的
I'm not going in first, though.
你先走 朵拉的感覺是對的
You go first, Dora. It feels right.
你們都沒什麼可擔心的
You all have nothing to worry about.
叢林非常安全！
The jungle is perfectly safe!
別碰任何東西或深呼吸
Just don't touch anything. Or breathe too deeply.
哦
Oh.
你確定你的父母會這樣走嗎？
Are you sure your parents went this way?
好吧 這些是什麼？
Okay, what are these?
警告信號
Warning signs.
圖騰
Totems.
傳說一個致命的古代民兵
Legend tells of a deadly ancient militia
致力於保護帕拉帕塔免 受外界的關注
dedicated to protecting Parapata from outside eyes.
沒有人見過消失的守護者...
No one has seen Los Guardianes Perdidos...
消失的守護者 幾個世紀以來
The Lost Guardians, for centuries.
那是什麼？
What was that?
克丘亞語
Quechua.
古印卡 令人印象深刻
Ancient Inca. Impressive.
這是什麼意思？
What does it mean?
所有那些尋求帕拉帕塔的人...
"All those that seek Parapata...
肯定會滅亡
shall surely perish."
好了 我已經準備讓我父母來找我了
Okay, I am ready for my parents to come and get me now.
你沒什麼可擔心的
You have nothing to worry about.
我保證 我是說 沒有必要反應過度
I promise. I mean, there's no need to overreact.
把它拿開！把它拿開！
Get it off! Get it off! Get it off!
這只是反應過度危險的例子
And that was just an example of the dangers of overreacting.
你沒事吧？
You okay?
沒事 完全沒問題
Fine. Totally fine.
嘿 我找到了一個紅色的圈
Hey. I found one of those red loops.
我父母的符號
My parents' symbol.
-我們一定越來越近了-哦 謝謝！
-We must be getting close. -Oh, thank you, thank you!
我們要回家了
We're going home.
這是我父母的營地
This is my parents' camp.
或者是 我是說 這是他們的東西
Or was. I mean, this is their stuff.
有人偷窺
Someone's watching.
我能感覺到
I can feel it.
哈哈！
Aha!
殺了它！快 殺了它！
Kill it! Quickly, kill it!
靴子！哦！
Boots! Oh!
哦 靴子 見到你真高興！
Oh, Boots, I'm so happy to see you!
她認識這隻猴子？
She knows this monkey?
她當然認識這隻猴子
Of course she knows this monkey.
謝天謝地
Thank goodness.
他看見他們了
He saw them.
哦 對不起 這是靴子 這些是我的朋友
Oh, sorry. This is Boots. Boots, these are my friends.
他們來幫我
They're here to help me.
不 我們是來求救的
No. We're here to get saved.
哦 還有 我們不是朋友
Oh, and FYI, we are not friends.
他們很快就做到了
They did this quickly.
-看看他們是怎麼畫的？-是的
-See how they rushed it? -Yeah.
不過 我比任何僱傭兵更能追蹤我的父母
Still, I can track my parents better than any mercenaries.
我們只需要先找到他們
We just have to get to them first.
我們能停下來嗎？我需要做一件事
Uh, may we stop for a moment? I need to do a thing.
-什麼？-隻是一件事
-What? -Just a thing.
什麼事？
What thing?
我知道是什麼
I know what this is.
-你必須大便 -沒有 不是這樣的
-You have to poo. -No. That isn't it.
我當然得大便！我已經48小時沒大便了！
Of course I have to poo! I haven't pooed in 48 hours!
我出汗了 每一步都是痛苦的！
I'm sweating, and every step is agony!
別看著我 摀住耳朵
Well, don't look at me cover your ears!
大概說了47次"摀住耳朵"
Probably should've said "cover your ears"
在你說"便便"之前
before you said "poo" like, 47 times.
別害怕
There's no need to be afraid.
我有個主意
I have an idea.
-讓我們把它變成一首歌 -我不要
-Let's turn this into a song. -Let's not.
你知道嗎？我想已經過去了
You know what? I think it's passed.
我們為什麼不回到這個小組 我們可以...
Why don't we just go back to the group, and we can just...
真的嗎？你的背包裏也太...
Seriously? You had that in your backpack, too?
一把糞便鏟
A poo shovel.
是時候挖個大屎坑
It's time to dig The poo hole
挖 挖
Dig, dig, dig
拿一把鏟子 這是一塊點心
Just grab a shovel It's a piece of cake
確保洞深 沒有蛇
Make sure the hole is deep And there isn't a snake
我告訴你 你會更聰明
I'm telling you this So you will be wiser
別忘了這是一種天然肥料
And don't forget It's a natural fertilizer
我相信你 薩米 我相信你能做到
I believe in you, Sammy. I believe that you can do this.
此外 在醫學上 你必須這樣做
Also, medically, you have to do this.
好了 再見！來吧 靴子
Okay, bye! Come on, Boots.
啊
Ah.
她很好
She's good.
沒什麼好怕的
There's nothing to be afraid of.
不好 一點也不好
Not good. Not good at all.
走 走 走！
Go, go, go!
真正的箭向我們飛來！
Real arrows flying at us! Real arrows flying at us!
挖糞坑
Dig the poo hole
挖 挖
Dig, dig, dig
啊！
Ah!
-快跑！-往外看！往外看！
-Run! -Look away! Look away!
-對不起 沒時間！-我們什麼也沒看見！
-Sorry, no time! -We saw nothing!
-為你的生命而跑！-我們得走了！
-Run for your life! -We gotta go!
啊！
Ahh!
-發生什麼事了？-這是詛咒！
-What is happening? -It's the curse!
詛咒會毀滅我們 我們要死了！
The curse is gonna perish us. We're gonna perish all over the place!
那裏 那裏！跟我來！
There, there! Follow me!
這邊！
This way!
我被擊中了！他們打我！我流血了！
I'm hit! They hit me! I'm bleeding out!
我失去了生命！
I am losing life force!
哦 不 不！果汁盒 只是一個果汁盒
Oh, no, no, no! No, it's a juice box. It's just a juice box.
我想我們很安全 就目前而言
I think we're safe. For now.
不安全 不安全！
Not safe. Not safe! Not safe!
我想回家！我想回家！
I want to go home! I want to go home!
我沒事！我沒事！
I'm okay! I'm okay!
夥計
Guys...
我不能肯定...
I can't say for sure...
我很有信心 我只是有些...嚴重的腦損傷
because I'm fairly confident I just sustained a... serious brain injury,
但我確實相信...
but I do believe...
我們可能剛剛見到了 消失的守護者
we may have just met Los Guardianes Perdidos.
消失的守護者
The Lost Guardians.
我以為你說他們只是傳說
I thought you said they were just legends.
這些是相同的印卡太陽符號 這些圖騰
These are the same Inca sun symbols that were on those totems.
還有這箭頭？
So these are like, legit arrows?
比如殺人箭？
Like, kill-people arrows?
標記是相當真實的
The markings are quite authentic.
嘿 你沒事吧？
Hey, you okay?
好
"Okay?"
好？
Okay?
不 我不好 好嗎？
No, I'm not okay, okay?
我想回家！
I want to go home!
我想盯著我的手機 在安靜的房間裏
I want to be staring at my phone, in an ice-cold room,
喝冷凍咖啡飲料！
drinking a frozen coffee beverage!
這是最基本的 但這就是我想要的！
And I know that makes me sound real basic, but that is what I want!
哦 順便說一下 唱歌也沒有
Oh, and by the way, the poo song lied.
是的 那很危險 箭落在我身上
Yeah, it was totally dangerous, arrows rained down on me.
我討厭這裏！
I hate it here!
嗯！嗯！
Uh! Uh!
我甚至不能出去 因為這個叢林會吃掉我！
And I can't even storm off 'cause this jungle will eat me!
也許一首歌會有所幫助
Maybe a song will help.
有時候 驚慌失措是可以的
It's okay To freak out sometimes
真的沒事...
It's really okay...
不再有歌了！
No more songs!
好
Okay.
你也是來對我大喊大叫的嗎？
Are you here to yell at me, too?
不 事實上 我來這裏是為了避免被大喊大叫
Nah. Actually, I'm here to avoid getting yelled at.
對別人負責是可怕的
It's scary to be responsible for other people.
當你獨自一人時 更可怕
It's easier when you're alone.
是嗎？
Is it?
聽著 我知道她有時會很痛苦 但是...
Look, I know she can be like, a real pain in the butt sometimes, but...
我猜她不全是壞人
she's not all bad, I guess.
你對她有吸引力
You have an attraction for her.
什麼？不
What? No.
不 我絕對沒說過
No, I definitely never said that.
你知道 一個危及生命的情況
You know, a life-threatening situation
可以經常加速許多物種的交配過程！
can often accelerate the mating process in many species!
好吧 不 放慢你的速度
Okay, no. Just slow your roll.
請不要再說"交配"這個詞了
And please don't ever say the word "mating" again.
-永遠 -嗯嗯
-Ever. -Mm. Mm-hmm.
我們離開這裏吧
Let's just get out of here.
我們走對了路嗎？
Are we even going the right way?
什麼
What?
狐貍的腳印
Fox tracks.
我偵察了這個地區北邊 有條新的小路
I scouted the area. There's a freshly-cut path to the north,
東邊有些廢墟
some ruins to the east.
-你找到他們的標記了嗎？-沒有
-Did you find any more of their markings? -No.
-好吧 我們往北走 -那是他們走的路
-Okay, then we head north. -That's the path they took.
-嗨 夥計們！-噓！
-Hi, guys! -Shh!
那是什麼？
What was that?
哦 啊
Oh. Ah.
啊哦！
Ah-oh!
你現在害怕猴子了？
What, you're scared of monkeys now?
猴子的體重是它們的三倍
Monkeys can carry three times their body weight.
是呀？毒蛇害怕猴子
So that's a yes? Viper's scared of monkeys.
這只是事實
It's just a monkey fact.
就是這些
That's all it is.
那些傢伙呢？
Where are those guys?
他們肯定死了 現在只有你和我
They're definitely dead. It's just you and me now.
答案是肯定的 我們得組建一個家庭
Of course... we'll have to start a family.
我們不是在組建家庭
We are not starting a family.
嗯 給它幾天
Eh, give it a few days.
嗯！嘿！你們去哪兒了？
Uh! Hey! Where have you guys been?
-嗨 夥計們 -我真的很抱歉 朵拉
-Hi, guys. -Look, I'm really sorry, Dora.
沒事的 很好 薩米
It's fine. It's fine, Sammy.
我們看見僱傭兵了 他們在我們前面
We saw the mercenaries. They're ahead of us.
我們必須從安全的距離跟蹤僱傭兵
We'll have to follow the mercenaries from a safe distance.
不 我們不跟著他們 我父母沒有走那條路
No. We're not following them. My parents didn't go that way.
我父親說去帕拉帕塔的路 要經過一個歌劇院
My father says that the way to Parapata passes through an opera house.
歌劇院建於幾百年前
The opera house was built hundreds of years ago
歐洲人在橡膠業繁榮的時期
by Europeans during the rubber boom.
到現在為止 除了廢墟 什麼也沒有
There'll be nothing but ruins by now.
這就是他們走的路
This is the way they went.
一定是這
This must be it.
可能吧
Or was it.
看起來 這裏很久沒歌劇歌手了
It doesn't look like any opera singers have been here for a while.
是的
Yeah.
歐洲人可能建造了它 但是...
The Europeans may have built it, but...
叢林把它奪回了
the jungle has taken it back.
哦 我的腳
Ew, my feet.
為什麼地面感覺像巧克力布丁？
Why does the ground feel like chocolate pudding?
對不起
Excuse me.
等等！
Wait, wait, wait!
我吃了很多的薯條和香腸
I ate a lot of frijoles and chimichangas.
我吃了辣椒
I ate chile con carne.
我會非常小心的
I ate mucho pozole.
嗯...
Um...
等等 有人注意到樹木在長高嗎？
Wait. Anyone else notice the walls are getting higher?
流沙！
Quicksand!
你開玩笑吧！
You got to be kidding me!
流沙真的存在嗎？
Quicksand really exists?
我以為只會在遊戲視頻中出現
I thought it was just a video game thing.
就像陷阱一樣！
Like Pitfall!
真棒
It's a classic.
我們怎麼擺脫這些東西？
How do we get out of this stuff?
好的 面對流沙 首先不要驚慌
Okay, rule number one of quicksand: don't panic.
那樣你會越陷越深
You'll only get sucked in further.
讓你的背平躺下來
Lie down flat on your back.
把體重分配到背上
You have to distribute your weight.
好 好吧
Okay. All right.
不 不 我不會這麼做的
No, no, no. I'm not doing that.
是的 不 這感覺不太對
Yeah. No, this feels super wrong.
現在用你的腿做小動作
Now make little movements with your legs
讓流沙騰出空間
to make space for the water to get between the sand.
一旦你的腿自由了 趕快從流沙中出來
And once your legs are free, simply backstroke out of the quicksand.
哦 讓我休息一下 我們會死在這裏
Oh, give me a break. We're gonna die in here.
看 看 她出來了！出來了！
Look, look! It's working! It's working!
加油
Come on.
謝謝
Thanks.
-幫幫我！-亞歷杭德羅 別動
-Help me! -Alejandro, you have to stop moving.
堅持...
Stay sti...
你們為什麼都安靜下來？
Why have you all gone quiet?
很糟 不是嗎？
It's bad, isn't it?
哦不！噓！
Oh, no! Shoo!
去！不 不！別在臉上
Cha! No, no no! Not on the face.
別不在臉上啊！
Not on the face. Ahh!
那個也是雄性 他們現在要戰鬥了
It's another male. They will now fight.
哦不！
No, no!
啊！
Ahh!
我覺得那傢伙不是在打架
I'm not sure those guys are fighting.
哦 是雌性
Oh, it's a female.
它們不是在打架 它們在交配！
They are not fighting. They are mating!
-把它拿開！-快 找樹枝
-Get it off! -Quick, someone go get a branch.
-我下沉了！-不 不 等等！
-I'm sinking! -No, no, wait!
夥計們 回來！
Guys, come back!
叢林裏滿是樹木 我卻找不到樹枝
It's a jungle full of trees and I can't find a branch.
哦 哦 不！
Oh, oh, no!
亞歷杭德囉！
Alejandro! Alejandro!
我看到腳了 人腳！
I see feet. Human feet!
這邊！
Over here!
好了 各位一二三！啊！
Okay, everyone. One, two, three! Ahh!
-我還活著？-是的！
-I'm alive? -Yes!
-我還活著！我還活著！-是的！
-I'm alive! I'm alive! -Yes!
我還活著 我還活著...
I'm alive, I'm alive...
我以為我會死
I thought I was gonna die.
大人們哭的時候 太尷尬了
It's so awkward when adults cry.
沒想到在這找到了他
You just don't know where to look.
我太蠢了！
And I was stupid!
然後有蝎子...
And then a scorpion went...
在我的頭上交配
mating on my head.
我很抱歉
I'm so sorry.
我一生都充滿了謊言
My whole life is a lie.
我是個騙子
I'm a fraud.
-不！不 -是的
-No! No. -Yes.
每個人都會犯錯 亞歷杭德羅
Everyone thinks that sometimes, Alejandro.
我是個壞人
I'm a bad guy.
-不 -是的
-No. -Yes.
-不 不 -不 是的 我是壞人
-No. No. No. -No, yes, I am. Yes.
我是個...我是個壞人！
I'm a... I'm a bad guy!
不 你不是壞人 沒有壞人 真的
No, you are not a bad guy. No one is, deep down inside.
-謝謝你 朵拉 -來吧
-Thank you, Dora. -Come on.
我們在哪？
Where are we?
有人住在這裏
Someone lives here.
有人要來
And that someone's coming.
她沒見過我的父母
She hasn't seen my parents.
她似乎 對幫我找父母不感興趣
And she doesn't seem very interested in helping me find them.
也許她知道如何去帕拉帕塔
Perhaps she knows how to get to Parapata.
帕拉帕塔！
Parapata!
她似乎對此很感興趣
She seemed pretty interested in that.
他們不會是我們嗎？
Are they supposed to be us?
嗯！
Yah!
看起來很糟糕 對吧？
That seemed bad, right?
-大家都覺得不好？-是的 有一點
-Everyone thinks that was bad? -Yeah, a little bit.
什麼？她說了什麼？
What? What did she say?
她說 尋求帕拉帕塔的人都會被詛咒
She said anyone seeking Parapata is cursed.
那太好了
Well, that's great.
但她也說 她知道如何讓你們回到下游
But she also said she knows how to get you guys back downriver.
她可以帶你們回家
She can take you home.
你們所有人
All of you.
是的 是的！我得救了！
Yes. Yes! I am saved!
我 是說
I... mean,
很顯然 你離開了我們 才能冷靜
only if you are cool without us, obviously.
你讓我陷入爛攤子 但我猜你把我救出來了
You got me into this mess, but I guess you're getting me out of it,
我們扯平了
so we'll call it even.
我和你一起去 我不能讓你一個人走
I'm coming with you. I can't let you go alone.
我是說 你是我的表妹 我該這樣做
I mean, plus you're my cousin. There's, like, rules about that.
這就是我們分開的地方
This is where we split up.
哦 我的...
Oh, my...
我 我希望你不要有事
I... I hope you don't die or anything.
你也是
You, too.
她在盯著我們嗎？
Is she staring at us?
-是的 -好 該走了
-Yeah. -Okay, time to go.
迭戈 朵拉 我們走
Diego, Dora, let's go.
-嗯？-她說要走這條路
-Hm? -She says stick to the path.
哦 我們走吧 再見 夥計們
Oh. Let's go. Bye, guys.
祝你好運 朵拉
Good luck, Dora.
-她為什麼這麼著急 要我們離開？
--Why is she in such a hurry to get us out of here?
蘭迪 等等 停下
Randy, wait, stop.
哦不 哦不！
Oh, no. Oh, no!
不 不 來吧！我們要告訴他們！
No, no, no, come on! We've got to warn them!
不是每天都能看到的
Not something you see every day.
你確定嗎？
Are you sure about this?
她說 這是我們必須走的路
Well, she said this was the way we had to go.
別碰任何東西
Don't touch anything.
真棒! 真棒!
Yes! Yes! Yes!
我們成功了！
We did it!
哎呀
Oops.
它吐在我的臉上！
It spat in my face!
-我們在孢子裏！-別吸氣！
-We're in a spore field! -Don't breathe it in!
-我們離開這裏！-沒事的
-Let's get out of here! -It's okay. It's okay.
如果這些是有毒的孢子 我們現在都死了
If these were poisonous spores, we'd all be dead by now.
來吧 迭戈 哦 哇
Come on, Diego... Oh, whoa.
什麼？
What?
-什麼？-哦 孩子
-What? -Oh, boy.
發生了什麼事情？
What's happening?
-你...你看起來很奇怪 -你也是
-You... You look weird. -You look weird.
-不 你看起來很奇怪 -你...不 你
-No, you look weird. -You... No, you.
-不 你！-你！你！他！
-No, you! You! -You! You! Him!
我不再需要這些衣服了！
I don't need these clothes anymore!
哦！
Oh!
天哪！
Blech!
我相信這一定會通過的 沒事的！
I'm sure this will pass. It's fine!
沒事？開什麼玩笑？
Fine? Are you kidding me?
太不可思議了！
This is incredible!
嗨 朵拉！
Hi, Dora!
嗨 地圖 哦 我以為你丟了
Hi there, Map! Oh, I thought I lost you.
你永遠不會失去我 我永遠和你在一起！
You can never lose me. I'm always with you!
嗨 朵拉
Hi, Dora.
背包！
Backpack!
我的嘴是拉鏈！
My mouth is a zipper!
-嗨 朵拉 -嗯
-Hi, Dora. -Hm.
-我不認識你 小石頭 -哦
-I don't know you, small rock. -Oh.
-但認識你真好 -啊
-But it's nice to make your acquaintance. -Ah.
大家都來了！
Everyone is here!
哇哦！
Whoo-hoo!
看 帕皮的日記！
Look! Papi's journal!
等等！
Wait!
哦！
Oh!
-哦-你沒事吧 朵拉？
-Ooh. -You okay, Dora?
我做不到 我還沒準備好
I can't. I'm not ready.
抓住我的手 讓我們一起試試吧
Take my hand. Let's try this together.
耶！
Yay!
薩米！蘭迪！
Sammy! Randy!
我們抓到你了 朵拉
We've got you, Dora.
謝謝 夥計們！
Thanks, guys!
-我們怎麼辦？-哦 我們應該給她唱首歌
-What do we do? -Oh, we should sing her a song.
她喜歡唱歌
She likes songs.
請活著 朵拉
Please be alive, Dora
不要有事
Don't be dead
聽起來好像
That sounds like something
你說的
That you would have said
-哦 我不太擅長這個 -成功了！
-Oh, I'm not very good at this. -It worked!
她醒了
She's waking up.
嘿！
Hey!
-蘭迪？-哦 謝天謝地
-Randy? -Oh, thank goodness.
靴子！
Boots!
哦
Ohh.
薩米！
Sammy!
-嗨 -你回來了
-Hi. -You came back.
-你的聲音很好 -嗯...
-You have a nice voice. -Well...
有時 一首歌挺好的
sometimes a song's the best idea.
哦
Ohh.
但不常唱
But not often.
哦 別告訴別人 我這麼做了
Oh, and don't tell anyone I did that.
你會沒事的
You're going to be okay.
你知道 朵拉 我...
You know, Dora, I...
我從未忘記叢林
I never forgot about the jungle.
還有你
And you...
你是我最好的朋友...
you were my best friend...
也我的第一個朋友
and my first friend.
我很高興和你在一起 朵拉
I'm glad I'm here with you, Dora.
我是說...
I mean, this...
這是我們的冒險 第一
this is our next adventure, prima.
我們的冒險 第一
Our next adventure, primo.
我 我做了一個奇怪的夢
I... I had the weirdest dream.
啊！啊！
Ah! Ah!
帕拉帕塔的入口 應該在這些山上
The entrance to Parapata should be somewhere in these mountains.
哦 太好了 第一次這樣
Oh, that's great. For the first time,
其實我感覺真的很好...
I'm actually feeling really good about how things are...
忽略我剛才說的話
Ignore what I just said.
哇
Whoa.
一切都藏在這裏？
This was all hidden down here?
好吧 現在我們被困在一個洞裏了
Well, great. Now we're stuck in a hole.
哇
Wow.
星星
Stars.
是星圖
It's a star map.
我們真棒
Classic us.
但是星星 不在正確的地方
But the stars aren't in the correct place.
令人驚嘆
Awesome.
叢林之謎！
It's a jungle puzzle!
我不認為這是叢林之謎
I don't think this is a jungle puzzle.
主要是沒有叢林之謎
Mainly because there's no such thing as a jungle puzzle.
聽著 我看過幾部關於叢林的電影
Listen, I've seen several movies about the jungle.
解決謎題 要把星星放在正確的位置
To solve this, we have to get the stars in the right place.
之後 這些大石頭轉動
And when we do, these big stone wheels will turn
寶藏就會出現
and the treasure will be revealed.
會很棒的
It's gonna be awesome.
我只是需要弄清楚
I just need to figure out
如何轉動第一塊
how to move the first piece.
哦
Oh.
你確定你應該碰那個嗎？
Are you sure you should be touching that?
什麼？
What is that?
聽起來不太好
That does not sound like a good noise.
哦 等等 星星在正確的位置
Oh, wait. The stars are in the right position.
是南半球
It's the southern hemisphere.
我只是看錯了
I was just looking at it the wrong way.
這還是個叢林之謎 對吧？
It's still a jungle puzzle, right?
哦！哦！我不認為這是叢林之謎
Oh! Oh! I don't think this is a jungle puzzle.
-這是機關 -在哪觸發的？
-This is a puquio. -What the flip is a puquio?
這是古老的地下渡槽
It's an ancient underground aqueduct.
印卡工匠建造了史上最複雜的灌溉系統
Inca engineers built some of the most elaborate irrigation systems ever devised.
水 從上面流下
Water, from above, using gravity.
哦 我的天哪  啊！
-Oh! -Ah, ah!
-哦 哦！-停止拉桿 蘭迪！
-Oh, oh! -Stop pulling levers, Randy!
啊！我在找開關！
Ahh! I'm trying to find the off switch!
好吧 如果這是渡槽 我們要打開水閘門
Okay, if this is an aqueduct, we just need to somehow open the sluice gate.
你怎麼知道這麼多關於水渠的事？
How do you know so much about aqueducts?
我們去年在歷史課上瞭解到了
We learned about them last year in history class.
你那周穿了很多紅色和粉紅色的衣服
You were there. It was the week you wore a lot of red and pink.
我一直在看你 好嗎？
I look at you a lot, okay?
我們需要找到水閘門 閘門在哪裏？
We need to find the sluice gate. Where is the sluice gate?
請不要說"閘門"
Please stop saying "sluice gate."
是控制水閘門的機關
That must be the mechanism that controls the sluice gate.
這樣說 好嗎？我們有重要的事情要處理！
That's what it's called, okay? We have bigger thing to deal with right now!
每個人都幫我一把 它會帶走我們所有人的
Everyone give me a hand. It's gonna take all of us.
一二三！
One, two, three!
這是我們最後的機會 趕快
This is our last chance. It's now or never.
誰能屏住呼吸七分鐘？
Who here can hold their breath for seven minutes?
這可能有點困難
It's hard to tell with all of this water,
但我願意試試
but I'm assuming none of your hands are raised.
還是我來吧
This one's mine.
哦！
Ohh!
哇啊！
Whoa, ah!
啊！啊！
Ah! Ahh!
啊！哇！
Ah! Whoa!
朵拉！
Dora!
-朵拉！-什麼？
-Dora! -What?
-哦 親愛的 哦 親愛的！-朵拉！
-Oh, honey. Oh, honey! -Dora!
-媽媽！-哦！
-Mami! -Oh!
-我的寶貝 女兒 -親愛的！親愛的！
-My baby girl. -Honey! Honey!
嘿！哦！
Hey! Ohh!
蘭迪做到了！我們還活著！
Randy did it! We're alive!
-塔蒂奧 -好吧 能有人告訴我 怎麼回事嗎？
-Tia, tio. -Okay, can somebody please tell me what's going on?
我們被找帕拉帕塔的僱傭兵綁架了
We were kidnapped by mercenaries who were after Parapata.
哦 我做了史詩般的事！我是個超級英雄！
Oh, I did something epic! I'm basically a superhero!
哦！
Oh!
嗨 朵拉的父母
Hi, Dora's parents.
好吧 親愛的 這些人是誰？
Okay, honey, who are all these people?
我們是朵拉的朋友 從學校來
We're Dora's friends. From school.
哦
Oh.
沒事的 好
It's fine. Fine.
我們正在進行實地考察
We're on a field trip.
僱傭兵呢？
And where are the mercenaries?
亞歷杭德羅把我們救了 他和我們在一起！
Alejandro saved us from them. And he's with us!
-誰？-你的老朋友
-Who? -Your old friend.
亞歷杭德羅 來自大學 你把日記寄給他了
Alejandro, from the university. You... You sent him your journal.
我的日記在探險前幾天被偷了
My journal was stolen days before the expedition.
布拉沃隊伍...
Bravo team...
我是阿爾法領袖
this is Alpha leader.
你不認識他 是嗎？
You don't know him, do you?
哦 奸細
Ohh. Miercoles.
-我們找到他們了-親愛的 過來
-We found them. -Honey, come here.
-回去 孩子們 -在德爾塔會合
-Get back, kids. -Delta rendezvous point.
你知道我的位置
You have my location.
-你騙了我 -不 不 不
-You lied to me. -No, no, no, no, no.
-不 我比你還聰明... -是這麼回事
-No, I outwitted you... -That's the same thing.
...因為我已經擊敗了你面前的對手
...as I have outwitted every adversary that came before you.
嘿！
Hey!
誰會相信
Who would have believed
我最大的成就
that my greatest achievement,
最終
the final act
在繁榮的探寶生涯中
in a prosperous treasure-hunting career
還要和不善社交的叢林呆子對決
would find me squaring off against a socially inept jungle nerd...
-嘿 嘿！-三個笨蛋學生
-Hey, hey, hey! -...and three high school losers.
我不認識他們 所以不管怎樣
I don't know them, so whatever.
現在 如果你願意的話...
Now, if you please...
你帶我去帕拉帕塔
you will lead me to Parapata.
但你不能進去 這是不可逾越的
But you can't get inside. It's impenetrable.
-"不可逾越！" -那意味著你不能進去
-"Impenetrable!" -That means you can't get inside.
-我知道！-好吧
-I know! -Okay.
閉嘴！
Shut up!
你不想讓她發生什麼事...
You wouldn't want anything to happen to her...
現在 你會嗎？
now, would you?
-當然不會 -很好
-Of course not. -Good.
很好 很好
Good, good.
如果都老實點 我會拿到我的金子
So, if everyone just plays nice, I'll get my gold,
你會在回家的路上安然無恙的
and you'll be on your way home safe and sound.
你是個聰明的家人 對吧？
You're a smart family, right?
因此 做出明智的選擇 嗯？
So make the smart choice. Hm?
我們走！出發！
We're moving out! Let's go!
我很抱歉 這都是我的錯
I'm so sorry. This is all my fault.
如果我們做他說的 我們就沒事了
If we do what he says, we'll be okay.
對不起 我很抱歉
Sorry, I'm so sorry.
不 我很抱歉
No, we're sorry.
-我們太愛你了！-是我們的錯
-We love you so much! -It's our fault.
你們能閉嘴嗎？
Can you all shut up back there?
三天來 我不得不聽你無心的理智！
I've had to listen to your mindless positivity for three days!
你無情的善良 是一場神聖的噩夢！
Your relentless good-natured spirit is a holy nightmare!
閉嘴！閉嘴！
So just shut up! Shut up!
-我很抱歉 -閉嘴！
-I'm so sorry about that. -Shut up!
別再說話了
No more talking.
也不要唱歌
And definitely no more singing.
你為什麼停在這裏？
Why have you stopped here?
就是這 對嗎？
This is it, isn't it?
不 不 不 它... -不 不 不
-No, no, no. It, uh... -No, no, no.
-嘿 等等 -不 求你了 等等！
-Hey, wait. -No, please, wait!
哇
Wow.
帕拉帕塔
Parapata.
是真的！
It's real!
我們今晚在那些大門前露營
We make camp tonight by those gates.
加油
Come on.
還行！
¡orale!
不 靴子 快走！不！
No, Boots, quit it! No!
爸爸要我們按他說的做
Papi wants us to do what they say.
靴子是為走路而做的
These boots are made for walkin'
後面發生什麼事了？
What's going on back here?
-哎呀 -孩子們！
-Oops. -Kids!
跑！
Run!
哇 這真是最致命的武器
Wow, it really is the deadliest weapon.
毒蛇！後面發生什麼事了？
Viper! What's going on back there?
放下
Put that down.
發生了什麼事？
What happened?
毒蛇他受傷了
Viper got yo-yoed.
-又來了？-又來了
-Again? -Again.
把教授們帶到門口去
Take the professors to the gate.
我和這些小妞在一起過幾天
I spent days with these brats.
我知道他們下一步會怎麼做
I know what they'll do next.
迭戈！薩米！
Diego! Sammy!
蘭迪！你們在哪裏？
Randy! Where are you guys?
靴子！
Boots!
你不應該那樣做！
You shouldn't have done that!
那麼 如果他是一個唯利是圖的尋寶者呢？
So what if he's a double-crossing mercenary treasure hunter?
我父母要給他看寶藏 他會讓我們都走
My parents are gonna show him the treasure and he's gonna let us all go.
他會殺了他們 不是嗎？
He's gonna kill them, isn't he?
他會殺了我們所有人
He's gonna kill all of us.
哦不
Oh, no.
我無法拯救他們
I can't save them.
就我一人
Not by myself.
我只是個孩子
I'm just a kid.
你不是個孩子
You're not a kid.
但你也不是大人 朵拉
But you're not a grownup either, Dora.
你是個少年
You're a teenager.
這是超級混亂的時刻
It's a super confusing time.
但事實是 你是對的...你不能自己去
But the fact is, you're right... you can't do it by yourself.
幸好你現在有了朋友
Good news is you have friends now.
在一起 任何事情都是可能的
And together, anything is possible.
靴子 你能說話嗎？
Boots, you can talk?
靴子 嘿 靴子靴子 來吧靴子
Boots. Hey, Boots. Boots, come on. Boots.
哦 哦 啊 啊 哦 哦...
Ooh, ooh, ah, ah. Ooh, ooh...
-嘿 你們聽到了嗎？-你跟猴子說話？
-Hey, did you guys hear that? -Uh, you talking to a monkey?
不 不 靴子在跟我說話
No, no, Boots was talking to me.
也許她撞到頭了
Maybe she hit her head.
來吧 夥計們 我們必須救我的父母
Come on, guys, we have to save my parents.
怎麼辦？我們還是玩溜溜球的青少年
How? We are teenagers armed with yo-yos.
亞歷杭德羅想要的只是金子
All Alejandro wants is the gold.
如果我們能進入帕拉帕塔
And if we can get inside Parapata,
我們可以用寶藏換我的父母
we can trade the treasure for my parents.
但是我們怎麼進入帕拉帕塔呢？
But how are we going to get into Parapata?
我們會弄清楚的 一起
We're gonna figure it out. Together.
今晚
Tonight.
守衛大門 我守衛著大門
Guarding the gate I'm guarding the gate
猛擊者守衛著大門
Swiper is guarding the gate
守衛大門 我守衛著大門
Guarding the gate I'm guarding the gate
你能停止唱歌嗎？真難聽
Would you stop singing? It's unprofessional.
我們怎麼從他身邊過去？
How are we gonna get past him?
守衛大門 我守衛著大門
Guarding the gate I'm guarding the gate
嗯？
Huh?
什麼東西？
Whatcha got there?
只是一隻小青蛙
It's just a little frog.
嗯？嗯
Huh? Hmm.
哦 哦 老天...
Oh. Oh, man...
幹得好 金毒青蛙
Good job, golden poison frog.
一定有辦法從外面打開大門
There must be a way to open the gates from the outside.
嘿 夥計們 看看這些
Hey, guys, look at these.
每個都有杠桿
Each one has a lever.
我對叢林謎題的看法是錯誤的 好嗎？
I was wrong about jungle puzzles, okay?
沒有叢林之謎
There is no such thing as a jungle puzzle.
等等 別這樣！看 陷阱
Wait, don't do that! Look. Traps.
可能是箭頭 或毒藥
Could be arrows, or poison.
好像到處都是陷阱
It looks like there's traps everywhere.
這是縝密的安全系統
This is one heavy security system.
那麼 我們怎麼知道要拉哪些杠桿呢？
So, how do we know which levers to pull?
有這麼多的組合
There are so many combinations.
什麼
What the...
夥計們 往下看
Guys, look down.
看起來像星座
Looks like constellations.
我們真棒
Classic us. Again.
這是亞瓦爾馬尤-印加夜空
This is Yawar Mayu, the Inca night sky.
啊 看 有些石頭亮得更久
Ah. Look. Some of the stones retain the light longer.
這是安卡-老鷹
This is anka, the eagle.
看
Look.
那是塔克-狐貍
And that's atuq, the fox.
那是 就在那兒
That's... right there.
這把看起來像條蛇
This one looks like a serpent.
-還有嗎？-這是奧托隆戈-美洲虎
-Are there any more? -This one's otorongo, the jaguar.
一定是第四個杠桿
This must be the fourth lever.
好吧 但是...我們先拉哪一個？
Okay, but... which one should we pull first?
也許我們一下子把他們拉了？
Maybe we pull 'em all at once?
嗯 這個可能性很大
Well, that's a pretty big maybe.
至少如果我們死了 我們一起死 對嗎？
At least if we die, we all get to die together, right?
喊三聲 我們拉
On three, we pull.
準備？
Ready?
一
One...
二
two...
三
three.
好吧 電影裏都是假的
Okay. It's official. Movies lie.
這是叢林之謎
It's a jungle puzzle.
是真的...害怕...叢林之謎
It's a real... freaking... jungle puzzle.
太棒了！很抱歉我懷疑你 電影
That is so awesome! I'm sorry I doubted you, movies.
我從沒見過這樣的事
I've never seen anything like it.
這是生命的發現！
This is the discovery of a lifetime!
我想這一定是寺廟
I guess this must be the temple.
金子 對吧？
The gold, right?
這就是黃金的藏身之處
This is totally where the gold's hidden.
印加人珍藏的一切都在這裏
Everything the Inca treasured will be in here.
但請記住...
But remember...
我們是探險家 不是尋寶者
we're explorers, not treasure hunters.
我們不是尋寶者 但亞歷杭德羅肯定是
We're not treasure hunters, but Alejandro sure is.
因此 我們要快
So let's be quick.
加油 我不做最後一個
Come on. I don't do last.
是空的
It's empty.
我不明白
I don't get it.
我沒看到任何門
I don't see any doors.
這不可能是寶藏
This can't be all that there is.
我沒有看到任何寶藏
I don't see any treasure.
它可能是被西班牙征服者清理出來的
It was probably cleaned out by Spanish conquistadores.
或者英國人或者是法國人
Or the British. Or the French.
或者美國人和聯合水果公司
Or the Americans and the United Fruit Company.
哦！啊！
Oh! Ah!
我找到了盤子 它可能是寶藏
I found this bowl. It could be treasure.
那是個太陽盤
That's a sun bowl.
你可以傾斜盤子 來反射陽光
You tilt the bowls to reflect the sunlight.
那一定意味著...
So that must mean there's...
看！牆上有一個開口 讓太陽照到
Look! There's an opening in the wall for the sun to shine in.
嗯 這個手電筒可以是我們的太陽
Well, this flashlight can be our sun.
來 靴子
Here, Boots.
哦！
Ooh!
呵呵 現在怎麼辦？
Huh. Now what?
我們必須盤子照到房間的正確位置
We have to angle the bowl to the right place in the room.
-很明顯他們喜歡幾何學 -它們對稱地組合在一起
-Clearly they loved geometry. -They fit together symmetrically.
-黃金比例！-51度
-The golden ratio! -51 degrees.
好吧 蘭迪 把你的盤子向迭戈傾斜51度
Okay, Randy, angle your bowl 51 degrees to Diego.
好
Okay.
好的 迭戈 照我
Okay, Diego... to me.
是的
Yeah.
好
Okay.
現在我要傾斜51度
Now I'll turn mine 51 degrees
我們看它照在哪裏
and we'll see where it lands.
一扇門！一扇門在打開
A door! It's opening a door, guys.
啊！哈！
-Ah! -Ha!
一直照射 直到門完全打開
Just hold the beam until the doors are fully open.
什麼？古代印加人團體擁抱？
What is that? Some sort of Ancient Inca group hug?
手滑了 對不起
It slipped. I'm sorry.
哦 夥計們...
Oh, guys...
-你可能想往上看 -嗯？
-you might want to look up. -Huh?
叢林之謎出現了！
The jungle puzzles are turning on us!
門關了！大家都快跑！
The door's closing! Everyone run!
來吧 靴子！
Come on, Boots!
朵拉 朵拉！試著把它拉開
Dora, Dora! Try and pull it open.
這還不行！
It isn't enough!
謝謝！謝謝！
Thank you! Thank you!
哦 靴子幹得好 夥計！
Oh, Boots. Good job, buddy!
哇 那是一條走廊
Whoa. That's some hallway.
它好像沒有盡頭
It's like it goes on forever.
-最終 -巨大的金絲猴(金神像)？
-At the end, is that... -...a giant golden monkey?
我們做到了 夥計們我們找到了寶藏
We did it, guys. We found the treasure.
等等 這些頭骨 看起來像...
Wait, these skulls, they look like a...
警告
warning.
拜託！
Oh, come on!
啊！矛頭！
Ahh! Spears!
好！我知道我們該做什麼
Okay! Okay, I know what we have to do.
當我們到達底部時 我們必須同時跳躍
When we get to the bottom of the hallway, we have to jump at the same time.
-太遠了！-什麼？我們不可能做到！
-It's too far! -What? We will never make it!
不 這是幻覺 好嗎？相信我
No, it's an illusion, okay? Trust me.
沒事的 薩米 放手吧 沒關係
It's okay, Sammy. Just let go. It's okay.
好
Okay.
三 二 一 去！
Three, two, one. Go!
現在！跳！
Now! Jump!
這點彫蟲小技 只能愚弄小偷和入侵者！
It was a forced perspective. A trick to fool thieves and trespassers!
幹得好 迭戈
Good job, Diego.
古印加團體擁抱勝利 夥計們
Ancient Inca group hug for the win, guys.
猴子(金神像)在後面 看起來更印象深刻
The monkey looked a lot more impressive back there.
看起來給我留下了深刻的印象
Looks pretty impressive to me.
-那是祖母綠嗎？-比籃球還大！
-Is that an emerald? -It's bigger than a basketball!
我想我們找到了寶藏
I think we found the treasure, guys.
不
No.
這是最後一個謎題
This is the last puzzle.
看
Look.
這是一句諺語
This is a quipu.
印卡書面語言
Inca written language.
"向上帝獻祭...
"Make an offering to the Gods...
最崇敬的
of that which is most revered."
印卡人之最？
What did the Inca revere the most?
很簡單！
That's easy!
和我一樣
The same as me:
黃金
Gold.
哦 克魯德
Oh, crud.
謝謝你為我渡過難關
Thanks for getting through the tough stuff for me.
又一次 我跟著你們知道了一切
Once again, I only had to follow Miss Know-It-All,
她直接帶我拿到了黃金
and she led me straight to the gold.
黃金 黃金！
Gold. Gold!
很多很多的黃金！
Lots and lots of gold!
這個謎題的答案很明顯
The answer to the puzzle is obvious.
印加人用它為神建造豐碑
The Incas built monuments to their gods with it.
黃金是印加人接觸到的 最像太陽的東西
Gold is as close to touching the sun as the Incas could get.
成功了！
It's happening!
我贏了！我贏了！
I beat you! I won!
我打敗了你 我贏了！哈
I beat you, I won! I beat you, I won! Ha!
寶藏就是我的了！
The treasure is going to be mine!
你誤會我 亞歷杭德羅
You were wrong about me, Alejandro.
我不是什麼都知道的人
I'm not a know-it-all.
但現在 我確實知道了你
But by now, I do know you.
我知道你會跟著我們來的
I knew that you would follow us in here.
我知道你會讓我們為你承擔所有的風險
And I knew that you would let us take all the risk for you.
我知道最後的考驗 會給應該失敗的人懲罰
I knew the final Inca test would carry dire consequences for those who should fail it.
這就是為什麼我們...
Which is why we...
在這裏 你...
are over here, and you...
你就站在那裏
Well, you're standing right there.
啊！啊！
Ah! Ahh!
哦！
Oh!
我還活著！
I'm still alive!
鮑威爾！毒蛇！
Powell! Viper!
幫幫我！到這兒來！現在！
Help me! Get in here! Now!
我的僱傭兵正在路上
My mercenaries are on their way.
這還沒有結束！
This isn't over yet!
-朵拉！-哦 親愛的！
-Dora! -Oh, honey!
媽媽！爸爸！我很抱歉
Mami! Papi! I'm so sorry.
沒事的 這很酷
It's fine. How cool is this?
看看這些傢伙 那是個真正的十字弓
Look at these guys, that's a real crossbow.
親愛的 那是個真正的十字弓
Honey. That's a real crossbow, yep.
是帕拉帕塔消失的守護者
It's the Lost Guardians of Parapata.
荒謬！沒有消失的守護者 我瞎編的
Ridiculous! There are no Lost Guardians. I made them up.
不 他們非常真實 夥計
No, they're super real, bro.
我警告過你們了！
你們還是一錯再錯！
我想我們要死了
I think this is when we perish.
抓住這些小偷！
不 等等
朵拉！
Dora!
我們和他不是一夥兒的
我們不是尋寶者
我們是探險家
我們是來學習的
證明給我看
探險家
-堅強點 親愛的 好嗎？-你能做到
-Be strong, honey, okay? -You choose the right thing.
是的
Yep.
她做到了
She did it.
明智的選擇
-謝謝 是的 -謝謝
-Thank you. Yeah. -Thank you.
親愛的
Honey.
我從來都沒...
It's like nothing I've...
沒想到
Ever imagined.
太驚人了
It's breathtaking.
猴子
Monkey.
真正的大金猴
Really big gold monkey.
跟你的小朋友說再見
Say goodbye to your little friend.
發生了什麼事情？
What is happening?
-猛擊者！-再見 失敗者！
-Swiper! -Adios, losers!
他激怒了眾神
大家趕快出去！
Everyone get out of here!
-金子呢？-不用管！
-What about the gold? -It doesn't matter!
等等 夥計們！那我呢？
Wait, guys! What about me?
你不能把我留在這裏！
You can't leave me here!
朵拉！蘭迪！幫幫我！
Dora! Randy! Help me!
我們是一個團隊 夥計們！
We're a team! Guys!
朵拉 來吧！
Dora, come on!
我知道了 答案是水！
I knew the answer was water!
你能再給我一次機會嗎？
Can you give me another go?
我在開金子的玩笑！不是金子！
I was joking about the gold! Of course not gold!
水才是金子！
Water is precious!
親愛的 我們走！
Honey, let's go!
你現在永遠也找不到它了 夥計！
And you'll never find it now, man!
我們得走了！我愛帕拉帕塔
We gotta go! I love Parapata,
但我不想永遠呆在這裏
but I don't want to be stuck here forever.
哦 哦
Uh-oh.
-靴子！-放開我 猴子！
-Boots! -Get off me, monkey!
哦！
Ow!
哦！哦 噢 哦！
Ow! Ow, ow, ow!
哦 丟人的傢伙
Oh, man. The indignity!
就是這樣
That's it.
-朵拉 不！-朵拉 等等！
-Dora, no! -Dora, wait!
你在做什麼？
What are you doing?
-哦 哇-啊！
-Oh, wow. -Ah!
朵拉！你做到了！
Dora! You did it!
我們應該掛個牌子 寫上"選水"嗎？
Should we put up a sign saying, "Choose the water"?
不？好吧
No? Okay.
朵拉
Dora...
你是一名偉大的探險家 朵拉！
世界上最偉大的探險家
我愛你
嘿
Hey.
這次旅行開始時 我們不是朋友 但我...
Look, I know we weren't exactly friends when this trip started, but I...
我也喜歡你
I like you, too.
-朵拉又盯著我們了 不是嗎？-是的
-Dora's staring at us again, isn't she? -Yeah.
好
Okay.
媽媽 爸爸！
Mom, Dad!
我們有一些令人興奮的消息
We have some exciting news.
幾周後我們就要回到叢林了
We're going back into the jungle in a few weeks.
我們要繼續探險 會幾個月都沒消息
We'll be gone for a few months, no contact, just us against the elements.
嗯 嗯
Mm-hmm.
我和你媽媽
Me and your mom.
還有你
And you.
我們開始做大事了 朵拉
We're onto something big, Dora.
關於那個
About that.
有人拉了杠桿 不知道是誰 但是...
Someone pulled a lever, not sure who, but...
-你 你！-你知道是誰
-You. You! -You know who it was.
我認為
I think...
我想回到城裏去
I think I want to go back to the city.
我很瞭解叢林
I know the jungle pretty well.
好
Okay.
但是高中...
But high school...
我想我需要更多的時間來研究那種文化
I think I need more time to study that culture.
-額 -額 -嗯
-Mm. -Mm-hmm.
還有城市裏的人
And its indigenous people.
-對 當然 -是的 嗯 嗯
-Right. Yeah, sure. -Yeah. Yeah. Uh-huh.
-那很好 -我愛你們
-That's good. -I love you guys.
-我們也愛你 -我們愛你 甜心
-We love you, too. -We love you, sweetheart.
哦 上帝 發生什麼事了？
Oh, God, what is happening?
-她現在有自己的生活了 -我為她高興
-She has a life of her own now. -I'm so happy for her.
我真高興
I'm so happy.
不會有事的 寶貝不會有事的
It's gonna be okay, babe. It's gonna be okay.
不會有事的！
It's not gonna be okay!
但我為她高興
But I'm so happy for her.
嘿 又多幾個笨蛋
Hey, look. The Dork-as multiplied.
哦 哇 我們做到了
Oh, hooray, we did it
我們在帕拉帕塔發現了黃金
We found the gold in Parapata
哦 哇 我們做到了
Oh, hooray, we did it
在南美洲深處
Deep in South America
哦 哇 我們做到了
Oh, hooray, we did it
我們在亞馬遜叢林中倖存下來
We survived the Amazon jungle
哦 哇 我們做到了
Oh, hooray, we did it
我認為皮疹是真菌所致
I developed a rash I think it's fungal
哇 哦
Whoa, oh
我們走在一起 這是真正的寶藏
We came together That's the real treasure
哇 哦
Whoa, oh
朋友們
Lo hicimos, amigos
我們會永遠是最好的朋友
We'll be best friends forever
哦 哇 我們做到了
Oh, hooray, we did it
有時候 會害怕
There were times when it was scary
哦 哇 我們做到了
Oh, hooray, we did it
我想我可能患有腹瀉
I think I may have dysentery
哦 哇 我們做到了
Oh, hooray, we did it
阻止了亞歷杭德羅和他的團隊
Stopped Alejandro and all his crew
哦 哇 我們做到了
Oh, hooray, we did it
And everyone saw me do a number two
Whoa, oh
We came together That's the real treasure
Lo hicimos, amigos
We'll be best friends forever
¡Vamonos!
Whoo!
Oh, hooray, we did it
Can someone get me out of here?
There were times when it was frightening
Oh, hooray, we did it
Swiper, no swiping!
Oh, man!
Ohh
Whoa, oh
We came together That's the real treasure
Lo hicimos, amigos
We'll be best friends forever
Whoa, oh
Llegamos juntos y ese es el gran premio
Como buenos amigos nuevamente lo logramos
Whoa, oh
We came together That's the real treasure
Lo hicimos, amigos
We'll be best friends forever